今日の聖句を見てみましょう
イエスはこう言いました
Now, if we think about Jesus’ words
in today’s text,
「今日 この日のためのパンを
私たちにお与えください」
“give us today our bread for this day,”
there’s really indirect counsel
イエスは暗に 物に心を奪われては
いけないと言っています
against materialism.
イエスはこう祈るようにとは
言いませんでした
See, Jesus didn’t say to pray
for our daily meat
「今日のためのお肉を下さい」
or some other luxury food item.
「今日のための豪華な食事を下さい」
また「1カ月分のパンを与えてください」
と祈るようにも言いませんでした
He didn’t even say that we should pray
for a month’s supply of bread
but to ‘pray for and be content
with our bread for the day.’
今日のためのパンを祈り
それで満足するようにと教えたのです
But, as we know,
a sizable number of Jehovah’s people today
でも エホバの証人の中にも
お金や物に心を奪われてしまった人が
大勢います
are being distracted by materialism.
これは決して人ごとではありません
So since this is not an imagined
私たちの間で現実に起きている問題です
but a real danger to Jehovah’s people,
let’s discuss the theme
それで今回は
“Beware of the Power of Materialism.”
「お金や物に夢中になるのは危険」
というテーマでお話しします
I recall the story
of a sister and her two sons
ある姉妹と2人の息子の
経験を思い出します
who were exiled to Siberia.
この親子はかつてシベリアに
流刑にされていました
Now, they were very poor.
とても貧しい生活をしていました
あまりにも貧しく
In fact,
they were so poor that at times
木の皮を剥いで食べなければ
ならないこともあったほどです
they had to literally eat
the bark off trees to survive.
極貧の生活でしたが みんなで
エホバに仕えていたので幸せでした
But they were happy
because they were all in the truth.
But years passed,
and the three of them had an opportunity
その後 何年かたって状況が変わります
3人でアメリカに
移住することになりました
to immigrate to the United States.
息子たちは給料の良い仕事に
就くことができました
The two sons got excellent jobs
—high paying jobs as machinists—
機械を扱う仕事です
but in their material prosperity,
いい暮らしができるようになりましたが
both sons fell out of the truth.
2人とも真理から離れてしまいました
姉妹は涙ながらにこう言いました
The sister tearfully remarked,
“I would rather be back in Siberia
「こんなことになるなら
シベリアにいて
“eating the bark off trees to survive
木の皮を食べながらでも
みんなで楽しくエホバに仕えていた方が
ずっとよかったです」
but with my two sons still in the truth.”
お金や物に夢中になるのは
本当に危険です
Well, numerous other experiences
could be related
こういう経験はほかにも
たくさんあります
that illustrate the power of materialism.
お金や物のことばかり考えさせる
In fact, it may well be
that Satan’s most effective trap
これはサタンが私たちに
仕掛けるわなの中で
against Jehovah’s people in these last days
一番強力なものかもしれません
is materialism.
でもちょっと待ってください
But now, you might be thinking,
‘Well, isn’t sexual immorality
会衆から排斥される
原因として一番多いのは
by far the number one cause
for disfellowshipping?’
性的不道徳ではないでしょうか
確かにそうです
That’s true, but we don’t have figures
for ones who fall away to materialism.
でも 物に心を奪われて離れた
人の数は分かりません
排斥されるわけではないからです
They’re not disfellowshipped.
And furthermore,
how many who succumb to sexual immorality
それに 性的不道徳に屈した人の中には
お金や物を愛するようになって
were first weakened spiritually
エホバとの絆が弱くなっていた人も
たくさんいるでしょう
by materialism?
Well, at least we can say that materialism
それで お金や物に
夢中になるよう仕向けることは
is one of Satan’s most effective tools,
or traps,
サタンが使う強力なわなと言えます
そのわなにはまってしまった人が
大勢います
against Jehovah’s people today.
今 サタンは
And it’s no wonder
that humans in Satan’s world
自分が支配する世界を使って
私たちにいろいろな広告や
宣伝を浴びせ掛けています
are bombarded
with so many advertising messages
designed to make us want things,
even if we don’t need these things.
本当は必要ない物まで
買わせようとしてきます
There was an Awake!{
以前の「目ざめよ！」の記事には
that discussed how Americans
こんな情報が載せられていました
アメリカ人は1日に1600もの
広告に接する とありました
may be bombarded
with up to 1,600 advertising messages
every day.
本当に膨大な量の広告です
Imagine that!
And none of us can feel we’re immune
自分はそういうものを見ても影響を
受けないなどと言える人は誰もいません
to this pressure
—that it can’t happen to us.
気を付けていないと いろいろな物を
欲しがるようになってしまいます
It could happen to any of us.
We could slowly, gradually,
少しずつ影響を受けて
begin to desire material things
本当は必要ない物まで欲しがるように
なってしまうのです
—even things we don’t really need.
In fact, that makes me think of the story
昔 ある巡回監督が
話してくれたことを思い出します
a circuit overseer told many years ago.
私が10代の頃なので
I was a young teenager.
50年以上前のことです
That was over 50 years ago.
He and his wife lived in a little trailer
巡回監督は 王国会館のそばに
止めたトレーラーで暮らしていました
they would park by the Kingdom Hall.
兄弟はある話の中で 電動ドリルを
買ったことに触れました
And he said in one of his talks
how he bought a drill
トレーラーで使うためのドリルです
to do work on his trailer.
But then shortly after he bought this drill,
でも買って間もなく 逆方向にも
回せるドリルが発売されました
they came out with a reversible drill.
And he thought:
‘Well, you know,
兄弟はこう思います
「これの方が便利だ
‘that would be nice
to have a reversible drill.
It would be much easier
to extract the drill bit out of the hole.’
このドリルがあれば これまでよりも
作業がはかどる」
兄弟はそのドリルも買いました
So he bought a reversible drill.
しばらくして また新しい
ドリルが発売されました
Shortly after that,
they came out with a reversible drill
今度はライトも付いています
that had a little light on it.
ドリルを回すとライトが光ります
兄弟はこう思います
You’d pull the trigger,
and a little light would come on.
And he thought:
‘You know, that would be really nice.
「すごい！ライトが付いてる！」
My drill doesn’t have a little light on it.’
He was about ready to buy this latest model,
兄弟は最新モデルも買おうとします
and then he said:
“Wait a minute!
でも ふと考えます
“What am I doing?
「いや 待てよ 夜 暗い中でドリルを
使うことなんて何回あるだろう？」
How often am I going to be drilling
at night?”
But he told that
to illustrate how materialism
兄弟はこういう話をして
必要ない物まで欲しくなることは
誰にでもある と教えてくれました
can get a hold of any of us.
兄弟は サタンの手口に
はまりそうになっていました
He was being manipulated by Satan’s system.
But now, here’s a question:
それで これからお金や物を
重視し過ぎないために
What Bible principles
can help us avoid this deadly trap,
materialism?
どんな聖書の原則が
助けになるか考えます
2つ取り上げます
Let’s discuss two.
Now, there are many others,
but these two can really help us.
特に役立つ2つの原則です
まず ミカ ７章を開いてみましょう
Let’s go to Micah chapter 7,
and let’s get this first Bible principle
that really can help us.
1つ目の役立つ原則が書かれています
Micah 7:7:
ミカ 7:7
「しかし私はエホバに目を向け続ける
［次です］
“But as for me,
“I will keep on the lookout for Jehovah.
“[now notice] I will show a waiting attitude
私の救いの神を
“for the God of my salvation.
辛抱強く待つ
My God will hear me.”
私の神は聞いてくださる」
Or the footnote says:
“I will wait patiently.”
「神を辛抱強く待つ」とあります
See, are we willing
to wait patiently on Jehovah?
良い物を手に入れることについて
辛抱強くエホバを待てるでしょうか
This certainly applies to material things.
Jehovah, in effect, is telling us today:
エホバは私たちに
いわばこう言っています
「今はあなたたちを
‘I’m giving you
‘a spiritual paradise right now.
比喩的なパラダイスに住ませている
それを楽しんでほしい
‘Be content with that.
今この世界で 自分のパラダイスを
つくろうとしてはいけない
‘Don’t try to get your physical paradise now.
I’ll give you that later.’
私を待ちなさい」
私たちは エホバを
辛抱強く待つでしょうか
But the question is,
Are we willing to wait on Jehovah, see?
それともエホバを待たずに
Or do we, in effect,
run ahead of him and try to acquire
自分のパラダイスを
つくろうとするでしょうか
physical paradisaic conditions
for ourselves right now
クリスチャンとしての
活動をおろそかにして
at the expense of spiritual activity?
良い物を手に入れることに
没頭するでしょうか
伝道の書 3:1には
こう書かれています
Ecclesiastes 3:1 says:
「何事にも時がある」
“There is an appointed time for everything.”
Well, Jehovah has appointed our time
エホバは今がどんな時で
何をすべき時かを教えてくれています
—especially these last days
of “the last days”
今は終わりの時代の
最後の最後の部分です
shortly before the last day
of this old system—
not as the time to seek and spend time
ですから今は 自分の
快適な暮らしのために
時間やエネルギーを
費やすべき時ではありません
acquiring physical comforts
but, rather,
as a time to beautify this spiritual paradise
むしろ 比喩的なパラダイスを
より美しくし
ほかの人もそれを楽しめるように
助けるべき時です
and help others join us in this paradise.
ペテロ第一 1:1と2:11では
No wonder at 1 Peter 1:1 and 2:11
私たちが「一時的居住者」
であると書かれています
God’s people are described
as “temporary residents!”
And it’s a real protection
if we think of ourselves that way:
自分が一時的居住者だと
意識することは大切です
temporary residents.
ホテルの部屋の例えをお聞きに
なったことがあるかもしれません
Now, the illustration has been used
of staying in a hotel room.
ホテルに泊まっている人は
一時的居住者です
Now, you know when you’re in a hotel room,
you’re a temporary resident.
You might do a few things
to make your stay more comfortable.
快適に過ごすために
ちょっとしたことをするでしょう
You might rearrange the chairs;
you might reposition the lamps;
椅子を動かしたり
ライトの位置を変えたり
you might buy some flowers
and put them on the table;
花をテーブルに飾ったり
するかもしれません
いい香りのスプレーを
まいたりもするかもしれません
you might spray some air freshener.
But you would never rip off the wallpaper
でも 壁紙をびりびりと剥がして
新しく張り替えたりはしないでしょう
and install new wallpaper.
カーペットを交換したりもしません
You’d never rip up the carpet
and install new carpet or tile.
新しい家具を買うこともありません
You wouldn’t buy new furniture.
大掛かりなことはしないでしょう
You’d keep it simple
そこには数日しかいないからです
because you know
you’re going to be checking out.
Now, even if you ended up
staying a few months in that hotel room,
たとえ いつチェックアウトするかが
決まっていなくて
especially if you didn’t know exactly when
you’re going to have to check out,
数カ月滞在することになったとしても
大掛かりなことはしないはずです
you would still keep it simple.
Well, that describes our situation.
私たちも同じような状況にいます
今の世界から「チェックアウト」して
We’re going to “check out”
of this old system.
新しい世界に「チェックイン」
しようとしています
We’re going to “check in”
to the new world.
We don’t know exactly when,
but we know it’s soon.
それは間もなくです ですから
So we keep it simple.
「一時的居住者」として
シンプルな生活を送るのです
We’re “temporary residents.”
But now, let’s get a second Bible principle
次に2つ目の役立つ聖書の原則を
考えてみましょう
that can help us avoid materialism.
Let’s go to Luke chapter 10.
ルカ 10章をご覧ください
ここでイエスが言ったことから
And Jesus’ words here
can help us identify
this second Bible principle.
大切な原則が学べます
At Luke 10:42, the B{
ルカ 10:42の後半です
“For her part,
「マリアは良いものを選びました
“Mary chose the good portion,
それが彼女から取り上げられることは
ありません」
and it will not be taken away from her.”
You notice she chose the good portion.
脚注によると「最も良いもの」を
選んだとあります
The footnote says the “best portion.”
Now, we know the story.
ご存じの通り マルタは食事の
準備に忙しくしていました
Martha chose physical activity.
キッチンで働くことを選びました
She chose working in the kitchen.
Mary chose spiritual activity
—listening to Jesus.
でもマリアが選んだのは
イエスの話を聞くことでした
Jesus correctly identified
who made the best choice,
イエスは最も良いものを選んだのは
マリアだと言いました
who chose the best portion.
マリアは良い手本です
Well, similarly with us,
when we choose
‘storing up treasure in heaven’
私たちも「地上に宝を
蓄える」のではなく
「天に宝を蓄え」たいと思います
over ‘storing up treasure on the earth,’
それが 最も良いものを
選ぶということです
we are choosing the best portion.
そうすれば エホバが喜んでくれます
How so?
Well, for one thing,
it brings Jehovah’s blessing,
私たちも幸せになれます
and that results in happiness.
格言 10:22には
次のように書かれています
We all know what Proverbs 10:22 says:
“It is the blessing of Jehovah
「エホバの祝福が人を富ませる
“that makes one rich,
それに痛みは伴わない」
and He adds no pain with it.”
一方 テモテ第一 6:9, 10には
In contrast,
1 Timothy 6:9, 10
お金や物を愛する人が
speaks about how those who go out
「多くの苦痛を
身に招［く］」とあります
for money or material things
脚注には「多くの苦痛で自分の
全身を刺［す］」と書かれています
can end up ‘stabbing themselves
all over with many pains.’
正反対の結果になります
Now, isn’t that a contrast
痛みの伴わない祝福と
—blessing from Jehovah with no pain
and stabbing yourself all over
with many pains?
全身を刺される苦痛です
Well, we’re choosing the best portion
when we go for spiritual, heavenly, treasure.
私たちは最も良いものを選び
天に宝を蓄えたいですね
Now, another reason is heavenly treasure
また 天に宝を蓄えているなら
新しい世界で暮らせるようになります
will result in preservation
into the new world,
if necessary by means of the resurrection.
今死ぬとしても復活があります
Proverbs 11:4:
格言 11:4に
“Wealth will be of no benefit
on the day of fury,
「富は激怒の日に何の役にも立たないが
正しい行いは人を死から
救い出す」とある通りです
but righteousness
is what will rescue from death.”
So remembering those two Bible principles
can really help us.
こうした聖書の原則を
覚えておきたいと思います
Remember that we are to wait on Jehovah.
1つ目の原則は エホバを
辛抱強く待つことでした
今は比喩的なパラダイスを
楽しみましょう
And he says,
‘It’s a spiritual paradise now
and a physical paradise later.’
エホバはもうすぐ地球全体を
パラダイスにしてくれます
We wait on him, and when we do that
(that second principle),
2つ目の原則は「最も良いもの」を
選ぶことでした
we’re choosing “the best portion.”
And we’re going to be happy.
We’re going to get Jehovah’s blessings.
そうすれば エホバに喜ばれ
幸せになれます
And if we do this, then, like Moses,
モーセのように「エジプトの宝より
価値がある」ものを
we’ll choose treasures
“greater than the treasures of Egypt.”
選んでいることになるのです
ではこれからもイエスが言った通り
We’ll be able to do what Jesus said
—to pray for and to be content
with our daily bread.
今日のためのパンを祈り
それで満足しましょう